Records of the Council on Hemispheric Affairs, 1975-2002 M1354
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Council on Hemispheric Affairs records
circa 1975-2002
M1354
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
221.5 Linear feet 443 manuscript boxes
The papers feature the materials related to the political, economical, and social development of Latin American region in the last quarter of the 20th century, its relationships with the U.S. and the nearby countries. The collection includes clippings, leaflets, various publications, newsletters, reports, correspondence, press releases, etc.)
Council on Hemispheric Affairs.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by the Council on Hemispheric Affairs to Stanford University, Special Collections in October 2002.
Access
Unprocessed; but open for research.
History
Founded in 1975, the Council on Hemispheric Affairs (COHA), a nonprofit, tax-exempt independent research and information organization, was established to promote the common interests of the hemisphere, raise the visibility of regional affairs and increase the importance of the inter-American relationship, as well as encourage the formulation of rational and constructive U.S. policies towards Latin America. In 1982, COHA’s board of trustees voted to expand its mandate to include monitoring Canadian/Latin American relations. Since its inception, COHA has been one of the most active and broadest-based U.S. private bodies dealing with the entire spectrum of political, economic and diplomatic issues, as well as responding to the economic and political challenges confronting the nations of this hemisphere. From its beginnings, COHA’s board consisted of the leadership of trade unions, professional organizations and religious groups, as well as civic and academic figures, who joined together to advance their common belief in support of representative government and pluralistic institutions throughout the hemisphere.
In recent years, COHA has directed a good deal of its research energies to such issues as unproductive U.S. pressure on President Aristide which eventually led to his ouster and Washington’s replacement with a hapless interim regime. COHA also has condemned Washington’s unexamined and reflexive policy towards Cuba and Venezuela, and the negative impact of neo-liberal reforms on the average Latin American. COHA was opposed to the adherence of the U.S. to NAFTA under the thesis that it shouldn’t have been initiated until basic Mexican institutions were truly democratic, its trade unions free enough to negotiate as equals, and the government purged of endemic corruption. COHA also is a critic of the indiscriminate application of structural adjustment formulas that end up negatively affecting the poorest stratum of Latin America’s population.
COHA is staffed by a small professional core, who contributes their services to the organization, supplemented by a large number of volunteer graduate and undergraduate students who often receive academic credit from their home institutions for the experience gained through their work with it. Over the years, retired government employees also have cooperated with COHA in preparing monographs on such topics as regional development, trade policies, and the controversial development strategies of the international lending agencies. The staff is assisted by a number of COHA senior research fellows from the United States, Latin America and elsewhere, who are generally considered to be leaders in their respective fields of expertise. It has been described on the Senate floor as “one of our nation’s most respected bodies of scholars and policymakers.”
from the Council on Hemispheric Affairs website.
Scope & Content
Collection was listed at the container level.
Latin America--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Latin America; United States--Foreign relations.
Container List
- Releases, publications, reports, typescripts, photocopies; 1990s mostly. (Box 1)
- Releases, publications, reports, typescripts, photocopies; 1990s mostly. (Box 2)
- Releases, publications, reports, typescripts, photocopies, fax copies; 1990s mostly. (Box 3)
- Releases, publications, reports, typescripts, photocopies, fax copies; 1990s mostly. (Box 4)
- Releases, publications, reports, typescripts, photocopies, fax copies; 1990s mostly. (Box 5)
- Releases, publications, reports, typescripts, photocopies, fax copies; 1990s mostly. (Box 6)
- Releases, publications, reports, typescripts, photocopies, fax copies; 1990s mostly. (Box 7)
- Press releases, 1987-1988; synopses, 1987-1988. (Box 8)
- Clippings, photocopies, faxes, typescripts, press releases, newsletters, miscellaneous (a lot of materials concerning Haiti politics). (Box 9)
- Press releases, photocopies, clippings, newsletters, miscellaneous (a lot of materials concerning Haiti politics). (Box 10)
- Press releases, 1982-1983. (Box 11)
- Press releases, 1984-1986; synopses, 1984-1986. (Box 12)
- Press releases, June 1976-1980. (Box 13)
- Press releases, 1981; typescripts, memos, clippings, etc. related to Venezuela. (Box 14)
- Clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous, mostly related to Venezuela, Virgin Islands, West India, and Uruguay. (Box 15)
- Clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous, mostly related to Venezuela and Uruguay. (Box 16)
- Materials related to Uruguay, Suriname, Puerto Rico, and Canada (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 17)
- Materials related to Puerto Rico; subject files - "Multiliteral development banks", "U.S. Military" etc. (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 18)
- Materials related to Latin America and Iran (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 19)
- Materials related to Iran, Latin America, and Japan (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 20)
- Materials related to Iraq, Kuwait, Guatemala, Mexico, Latin America in general (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 21)
- Materials related to NAFTA mostly (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 22)
- Materials related to NAFTA; miscellaneous files (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints). (Box 23)
- Materials related to NAFTA; miscellaneous files (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, correspondence). (Box 24)
- Materials related to NAFTA; miscellaneous files (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, correspondence). (Box 25)
- Materials related mostly to Mexico (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, correspondence). (Box 26)
- Materials related mostly to Mexico (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, correspondence). (Box 27)
- Materials related to Mexico and NAFTA mostly (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, correspondence, internship applications, accomplishment forms, intern information sheets). (Box 28)
- Materials related mostly to Mexico (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 29)
- Materials related mostly to Mexico (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 30)
- Materials related mostly to Mexico and Nicaragua (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 31)
- Materials related mostly to Mexico and Nicaragua (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 32)
- Materials related mostly to Nicaragua and Honduras (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 33)
- Materials related to Nicaragua (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 34)
- Materials related to Nicaragua and Panama (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 35)
- Materials related to Panama and personally General Noriega (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 36)
- Materials related to Panama, Honduras, and Costa Rica (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 37)
- Materials related to Panama (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 38)
- Materials related to Panama and Columbia (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 39)
- Materials related to Columbia, Chile, Peru, and Paraguay (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 40)
- Materials related to Columbia, Peru, and Paraguay (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 41)
- Materials related to Columbia, Chile, and Peru (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 42)
- Materials related to Peru and Paraguay (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 43)
- Materials related to Cuba (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 44)
- Materials related to Cuba, Cuba - U.S. relations (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 45)
- Materials related to Cuba, Cuba - Latin America relations (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 46)
- Materials related to Cuba and Dominican Republic (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 47)
- Materials related to Dominican Republic, Ecuador, and El Salvador (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, miscellaneous). (Box 48)
- Materials related to El Salvador and Guyana (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, tear sheets, miscellaneous). (Box 49)
- Materials related to El Salvador, Guyana, and Grenada (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, tear sheets, miscellaneous). (Box 50)
- Materials related to El Salvador and Ecuador (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, tear sheets, miscellaneous). (Box 51)
- Materials related to Ecuador and Dominican Republic, COHA internal documents (clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, tear sheets, correspondence files, miscellaneous). (Box 52)
- Clippings, publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, tear sheets, correspondence files, reports, notes, miscellaneous. (Box 53)
- Publications, faxes, photocopies, newsletters, off-prints, tear sheets, correspondence files, reports, notes, resumes, miscellaneous. (Box 54)
- Clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous. (Box 55)
- Materials related to Argentina and Barbados (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 56)
- Materials related to "Argentina-Economy" and "Argentina-Brazil Relations" (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 57)
- Materials related to Argentina (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 58)
- Materials related to Brazil and Bolivia (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 59)
- Materials related to "Brazil-Collor Scandal" and Bolivia (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 60)
- Materials related to Bahamas, Bolivia, Belize, and Canada (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 61)
- Materials related to Canada (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 62)
- Materials related to Brazil and Canada (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 63)
- Materials related to Brazil and Canada (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 64)
- Materials related to Brazil and Nicaragua, mostly regarding elections (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 65)
- Materials related to Nicaragua and El Salvador (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 66)
- Materials related to Nicaragua (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 67)
- Materials related to Nicaragua (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 68)
- Materials related to Mexico, Guatemala, El Salvador, Trinidad and Tobago, Venezuela, Uruguay, Honduras, Paraguay, Panama, Peru, Nicaragua, Grenada, and Ecuador (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 69)
- Materials related to Dominican Republic, Barbados, Pentagon; subject files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, posters, miscellaneous). (Box 70)
- Press materials. (Box 71)
- Materials related to Canada and Chile (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 72)
- Materials related to Canada, Chile, Caribbean, "Canada-Latin America Relations"; miscellaneous files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 73)
- Materials related to Canada, Chile, Caribbean, French Guinea, Cuba, and Dominican Republic (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 74)
- Materials related to Cuba, Canada, Guatemala, and Peru (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 75)
- Materials related to Latin America-General, Chile, Jamaica, Columbia, El Salvador, Trinidad and Tobago, Nicaragua; miscellaneous files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 76)
- Materials related to Haiti, Cuba, Costa Rica, Argentina, Belize, and Bolivia (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 77)
- Materials related to Bolivia, Brazil, and Canada (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 78)
- Materials related to Canada, Chile, Caribbean, Columbia, and Costa Rica (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, miscellaneous). (Box 79)
- Materials related to Costa Rica, Ecuador, Guyana, Haiti, Honduras, Jamaica; miscellaneous files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 80)
- Materials related to Mexico; miscellaneous files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 81)
- Materials related to Mexico, Nicaragua; miscellaneous files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 82)
- Materials related to Mexico (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 83)
- Materials related to Mexico, "United Nations Conference on Environment and Development"; miscellaneous files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 84)
- Materials related to Suriname; miscellaneous subject files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 85)
- Materials related to Paraguay; miscellaneous subject files - NAFTA etc. (lippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 86)
- Materials related to Panama, U.S.; miscellaneous subject files - NAFTA etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 87)
- Materials related to Peru, Puerto Rico, Venezuela, Uruguay; miscellaneous subject files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 88)
- Subject files - NAFTA etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 89)
- Subject files - "Child Labor," "Coffee," "NAFTA," etc.; personal files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 90)
- Materials related to Central America, Honduras, China, El Salvador; subject files - "Central American Historical Institute", miscellaneous (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 91)
- Subject files - "Clinton", "Cholera", "Abortion" etc.; personal files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 92)
- Subject files - "AIDS", etc.; personal files - "Abrams, Elliot", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 93)
- Subject files on Caribbean Basin Initiative, etc.; materials related to Canada (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 94)
- Materials related to Central America, Paraguay, Suriname, Uruguay; subject files - "NAFTA", "Environment", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 95)
- Materials related to Argentina, Bolivia, Cuba; miscellaneous subject files - "Immigration", "Drugs", "Diseases", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 96)
- Materials related to Argentina, Brazil, Canada, Chile, Columbia; miscellaneous (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 97)
- Materials related to Columbia, Costa Rica, Cuba, Cuba-U.S. Relations, Haiti (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 98)
- Materials related to Ecuador, El Salvador, Haiti, Nicaragua (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 99)
- Materials related to Nicaragua, Latin America (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 100)
- Materials related to Nicaragua and Mexico; miscellaneous (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 101)
- Materials related to Nicaragua, Guatemala, Costa Rica (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 102)
- Materials related to Guatemala (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 103)
- Materials related to Guatemala - continued (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 104)
- Materials related to Bolivia, Ecuador, Dominican Republic; miscellaneous (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 105)
- Materials related to Bolivia, Ecuador, Dominican Republic - continued; miscellaneous (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 106)
- Materials related to Bolivia (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 107)
- Materials related to Bolivia and Ecuador (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 108)
- Materials related to Ecuador, Dominican Republic, Cuba-U.S. relations; miscellaneous (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 109)
- Materials related to Honduras, El Salvador - mostly about human rights; personal files; miscellaneous files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 110)
- Personal and subject files - "Reagan", "Poindexter, John" (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 111)
- Materials related to El Salvador; personal files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 112)
- Materials related to Nicaragua, Saudi Arabia, Honduras, El Salvador - mostly regarding human rights; miscellaneous files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 113)
- Materials regarding Ct. Colonel Oliver L. North, Nicaragua (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 114)
- Materials related to El Salvador - human rights, 1983-1985, no date (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 115)
- Materials related to Columbia - "Drugs", "General" (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 116)
- Materials related to Columbia (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 117)
- Materials related to Columbia, continued (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 118)
- Materials related to Columbia, Canada, Chile materials; thematic / subject files (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 119)
- Subject files - "Children", "World Bank", "U.S. Foreign Policy", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 120)
- Materials related to Cuba; subject files - "Education", "Environment", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 121)
- Materials related to El Salvador; subject files - "Immigration", "National Endowment for Democracy", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 122)
- Materials related to Iran; subject files - "Latin American Infrastructure", "U.S. Immigration", "Refugees", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 123)
- Subject files - "Immigrants / Refugees", "U.S. Media - miscellaneous", "Voices of America", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 124)
- Materials related to Dominican Republic, Ecuador, Honduras, Grenada, Guyana, Columbia, Iran; subject files - "Refugees", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 125)
- Subject files - "Pan American Health Organization", "NAFTA 1993", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 126)
- Subject files - "North trial", "Oil / OPEC", etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 127)
- Subject files - "NAFTA", "Clinton - Latin America," "Negroponte," etc. (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 128)
- Documents regarding COHA (Council on Hemispheric Affairs) interns (correspondence, personal data sheets, instructions, bulletins, reports, typescripts, leaflets, publications, miscellaneous). (Box 129)
- Documents regarding COHA (Council on Hemispheric Affairs) interns (correspondence, personal data sheets, instructions, bulletins, reports, typescripts, leaflets, publications, miscellaneous); materials related to Guatemala (personal files; clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 130)
- Materials related to Guatemala (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.); miscellaneous files (statements, bulletins, newsletters, photocopies, etc.). (Box 131)
- Materials related to Brazil (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 132)
- Materials related to Brazil, continued (clippings, leaflets, publications, reports, correspondence, releases, etc.). (Box 133)